<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-11-19T10:33:00-03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Mainframe Open Education</title><subtitle>A website with blog posts and pages</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Mainframe Fundamental Skills</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/09/06/mf-fundamentals-concepts.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mainframe Fundamental Skills" /><published>2021-09-06T00:00:00-03:00</published><updated>2021-09-06T00:00:00-03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/09/06/mf-fundamentals-concepts</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/09/06/mf-fundamentals-concepts.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;mainframe-fundamental-skills&quot;&gt;Mainframe Fundamental Skills&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By now, you should already know what a Mainframe is; as a next step, we prepared a section for those looking for guidance about Mainframe architecture and software. 
The objective of this session is to share with you the initial information about the Foundation concepts about the Mainframe architecture, how and from where you should start.
There are some excellent courses available for the community at no cost that we will share here. As education is constantly evolving, we encourage you to share the existing guidance with anyone interested in learning about the Mainframe or with experts who are willing to add value and new content to this section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We hope you enjoy it!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;digital-certificate-badges&quot;&gt;Digital Certificate Badges&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since 2016, a new way of learning and earning credentials in the IT world has been launched. The Digital Certificated Badges allow you to share your achievements with your social media easily. The Badges are based on a specific topic and expertise area. As you learn, you earn badges to add to your curriculum, on your social media, and share with others. It is a great new way of learning that helps you increase your skills while also engaging the community. The Mainframe ecosystem embraced this approach, and we can find most of the Mainframe content in a Badge layout. In this section, you will find some initial recommendations, free of charge, to earn Badges and start to leverage your skills in Mainframe&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;zos-mainframe-practitioner&quot;&gt;z/OS Mainframe Practitioner&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One good recommendation to start is the z/OS Mainframe Practitioner Badge. It was created by IBM.
Badge Description: This badge earner has developed foundational skills in IBM Z hardware and software, especially around z/OS and System Administration. Through hands-on labs working on a live IBM Z server, the earner has gained real-world experience and is equipped to pursue a career as a mainframe application developer, system programmer, system administrator, or DBA Practitioner.
Skills: Technical Specialist | Security | Telecommunications | Adaptability &amp;amp; Flexibility | Linux | Mainframe | Z Systems | IBM z
To earn the badge, follow the instructions on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ibm.com/training/badge/223baff0-38b6-4722-be90-016e7d5ea404&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-it-takes-to-earn-this-badge&quot;&gt;What it takes to earn this badge&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Complete all courses in the z/OS Mainframe Practitioner Professional Certificate program on Coursera (including quizzes, hands-on assignments, and projects), and earn the following badges:
 Introduction to Enterprise Computing badge.
 Getting Started on Mainframe with z/OS Commands and Panels badge.
 Basic System Programming on IBM Z badge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;new-topics-to-be-released-soon&quot;&gt;New topics to be released soon:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1 Glossary (Acronyms mainframe related)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;how-to-contribute-to-this-section&quot;&gt;How to contribute to this section?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Go to &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/openmainframeproject/omp-education&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Follow the steps described in the README file&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Mainframe" /><category term="Z" /><category term="IT" /><category term="Technology" /><summary type="html">Mainframe Fundamental Skills By now, you should already know what a Mainframe is; as a next step, we prepared a section for those looking for guidance about Mainframe architecture and software. The objective of this session is to share with you the initial information about the Foundation concepts about the Mainframe architecture, how and from where you should start. There are some excellent courses available for the community at no cost that we will share here. As education is constantly evolving, we encourage you to share the existing guidance with anyone interested in learning about the Mainframe or with experts who are willing to add value and new content to this section.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What is a Mainframe?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/08/30/what-is-a-mainframe.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is a Mainframe?" /><published>2021-08-30T00:00:00-03:00</published><updated>2021-08-30T00:00:00-03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/08/30/what-is-a-mainframe</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/08/30/what-is-a-mainframe.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-is-mainframe&quot;&gt;What is Mainframe&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mainframes are computers. They are known for their vast capacity, high performance, large amounts of memory, and processors.  Mainframe computers can handle many tasks concurrently, and they are critical to commercial databases, transaction servers, and applications that require high resiliency, security, and agility.
For that reason, these computers are robust, rugged, reliable, secured, and available for nonstop &lt;strong&gt;24×7&lt;/strong&gt; operations.
Behind the complexity of this enormous computer, it is closer to you than you would imagine. You might never hear about the Mainframe; however, it has been with you since you wake up in the morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;who-uses-the-mainframe-and-why&quot;&gt;Who Uses the Mainframe and why?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might not know, but the Mainframe is part of your daily routine. You are not a direct user of it, but you definitely are an end-user of most financial, enterprise, retail, and data management transactions we interact with during your day. All types and sizes of businesses and organizations can leverage the Mainframe as technology to support your business. The most common are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Big organization to manage enterprise-wide mission-critical ERP operations,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Banks to handle to trillion of transactions,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Back-end operations of many digital applications.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Topics to explore more: Role of the Mainframe Today: Why is it so relevant today? Talk about hybrid cloud, how it influenced IT today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;mainframe-basic-architecture--components&quot;&gt;Mainframe Basic Architecture &amp;amp; Components&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mainframe-key-components&quot;&gt;Mainframe Key Components&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mainframe In the past, the term Mainframe was synonymous with the hardware (S360/370/390 chips) and software (MVS, VM, VSE).  However, nowadays, the term Mainframe now has a more complex meaning.
 The term Mainframe must be divided into two meanings:
The hardware (Z-Series chip) 
The operating systems that are supported by the Z-Series chip (Z/VM, Z/OS, Z/VSE, Linux).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mainframe-hardware&quot;&gt;Mainframe Hardware&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Z-Series CPU chips:  Supports Z/VM, Z/OS, Z/VSE, Linux operating systems, and open-source software.  It also supports Hybrid Cloud technology.  Mainframe hardware includes outboard I/O and encryption CPUs, Hyper Channels, redundant power supplies, and resilience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mainframe-software&quot;&gt;Mainframe Software&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Z-Series software: this software is traditionally referred to as VM, z/VM, MVS, MVS/XA, MVS/ESA, z/OS, VSE, or z/VSE.  These operating systems have evolved and been used over the last 50 years.  Mainframe software has evolved from a purely batch-oriented system using only JCL to incorporating real-time interfaces and Unix System Service.  Mainframe software has progressed to being compatible with distributed systems, the most notable innovation being ZOWE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;virtual-tour-on-a-mainframe&quot;&gt;Virtual Tour on a Mainframe&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We want to invite you to do an online tour inside the Mainframe Hardware.  In this Virtual tour, you can reach the mainframe machine, open doors, remove switches and understand how Mainframe Hardware looks today. Click &lt;a href=&quot;http://m.kaon.com/c/ib&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, then choose the &lt;strong&gt;“Run Online/Web”&lt;/strong&gt; Option, after we recommend to start from the &lt;strong&gt;“System/Server”&lt;/strong&gt;, IBM Z is the Mainframe. Then you just need to click on the latest machine type, which will be on the top of the list. Once you join the machine, you might find “Explore Product Animation” where you can navigate all the machine details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;mainframe-brief-history-and-timeline&quot;&gt;Mainframe brief History and Timeline&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mainframe mission from the ’50s until the 21st century, and its future. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.computerhistory.org/revolution/mainframe-computers/7/166&quot;&gt;Learn more about Mainframe history&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;mainframe-versus-servers&quot;&gt;Mainframe versus Servers&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have never heard about Mainframe, a good starting point is to compare it with the most common Servers for end-users. You can find the comparison table to bridge the existing knowledge with the Mainframe concepts and capacity &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.educba.com/mainframe-vs-server/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;how-to-contribute-to-this-section&quot;&gt;How to contribute to this section?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Go to &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/openmainframeproject/omp-education&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Follow the steps described in the README file&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Mainframe" /><category term="Z" /><category term="IT" /><category term="Technology" /><summary type="html">What is Mainframe Mainframes are computers. They are known for their vast capacity, high performance, large amounts of memory, and processors. Mainframe computers can handle many tasks concurrently, and they are critical to commercial databases, transaction servers, and applications that require high resiliency, security, and agility. For that reason, these computers are robust, rugged, reliable, secured, and available for nonstop 24×7 operations. Behind the complexity of this enormous computer, it is closer to you than you would imagine. You might never hear about the Mainframe; however, it has been with you since you wake up in the morning.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Roles in Mainframe</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/04/27/Roles-in-Mainframe.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Roles in Mainframe" /><published>2021-04-27T00:00:00-03:00</published><updated>2021-04-27T00:00:00-03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/04/27/Roles-in-Mainframe</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/04/27/Roles-in-Mainframe.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;roles-in-mainframe&quot;&gt;Roles in Mainframe&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the market, we can find many professionals with mainframe skills as part of their background. There are different skills sets and expertise that build each of them. This section will review the most common roles having Mainframe as a background skill and a high-level description of skills expertise required for each of them. 
If you are a mainframe professional, please share your role and the skills required to build your expertise. It will add a lot of value to our community!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;infrastructure-services&quot;&gt;Infrastructure Services&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;it-system-management&quot;&gt;IT System Management&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;System Operator&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Production Analyst&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;it-specialist&quot;&gt;IT Specialist&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;System Programmer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;System Administrator&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Architect&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;software-development&quot;&gt;Software Development&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Application Software Developer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;application-specialist&quot;&gt;Application Specialist&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Business Application Package&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Business Application System&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;customer-services&quot;&gt;Customer Services&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Customer Engineer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Facility Manager&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Software/Product Manager&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hardware Manager&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;it-architect&quot;&gt;IT Architect&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Application Architect&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Software Architect&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Integration Architect&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;project-management&quot;&gt;Project Management&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;System Development&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;IT outsourcing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Software Product Development&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Network Services&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;education&quot;&gt;Education&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Instructors&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Training Program Manager&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sales--marketing&quot;&gt;Sales &amp;amp; Marketing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Consultant&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sellers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Communication&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Industry&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;how-to-contribute-to-this-section&quot;&gt;How to contribute to this section?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Go to &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/openmainframeproject/omp-education&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Follow the steps described in the README file&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Mainframe" /><category term="Z" /><category term="IT" /><category term="Technology" /><category term="Roles" /><category term="Professions" /><category term="Job" /><summary type="html">Roles in Mainframe</summary></entry></feed>